YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 3. National Administrative Office
Sophia Smith Collection
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records: Record Group 03. National Administrative Office
1906-2002
Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.
324_rg3
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This record group consists of the YWCA's national administrative office files including the office of the General Secretary (later Executive Secretary, later Chief Executive Officer) records on buildings and properties owned by the national organization, finance and development files, and records of the departments of data and statistics, library and archives, and publicity. Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records.
Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records.
NOTE: For the most part, the Microfilmed Records and the Original Format Records do not duplicate each other and both should be consulted. This description covers materials in both formats. See the Contents List for a folder-level inventory of the Original Format Records. See the Microfilmed Records Reel Lists for a detailed inventory of the microfilm. Links to the lists for both formats are provided in the Series Descriptions.
This record group consists of the YWCA's national administrative office files including the office of the General Secretary (later Executive Secretary, later Chief Executive Officer) records on buildings and properties owned by the national organization, finance and development files, and records of the departments of data and statistics, library and archives, and publicity.
This Record Group is divided into six Series:
I. GENERAL ADMINISTRATION
II. BUILDINGS AND PROPERTIES
III. FINANCE AND DEVELOPMENT
IV. DATA AND STATISTICS
V. LIBRARY AND ARCHIVES
VI. PUBLICITY
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
Additional Formats
A copy of the microfilmed records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records is available to borrow from the William Allan Neilson Library at Smith College via Interlibrary Loan.
To request the microfilm from our library you will need to submit the following information to your library's Interlibrary Loan department:
Author: Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. National Board
Title: Records, 1876-1970 [microform]
WorldCat Accession Number: OCLC 57415795
Notes: "Call # 689" and reel number(s) you want to borrow
Full descriptions and reel lists of the microfilm are available online.
The YWCA of the U.S.A. donated a portion of its records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1964 and the remainder in 2002 and 2003.
African Americans--Civil rights--History--20th century--Sources; American College for Girls (Istanbul, Turkey); Anti-communist movements--United States--History--Sources; Civil rights movements--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Nonprofit organizations--Management; Norris, Elizabeth, 1914-2003; Race awareness--United States; Race relations--United States; United Service Organizations (U.S.); World Young Women's Christian Association; Young Men's Christian Association
Record Groups
The YWCA of the USA Records are arranged as follows:
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records (main record)
RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY
RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD
RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE
RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES
RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK
RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM
RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK
RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
Artifacts
The Microfilmed Records
The Oversized Materials
This Record group forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records
Series Descriptions
- SERIES I. GENERAL ADMINISTRATION
  Historical Note
  For most of the 20th century, "General Administration" was the name of the administrative office with its related support services for officers of the National Board and national staff. These included the President, Vice-Presidents, Secretary, and Treasurer of the National Board; and the executive officer of the national staff, known as General Secretary (1906-66), Executive Director (1967-ca.1990), National Executive Director (ca. 1991-96); and Chief Executive Officer (1997-2002).
  General Administration was the public face of the National Association, shepherding public perception from appearances and speeches, to receiving and responding to criticism, to serving on committees, commissions, and boards of related organizations, particularly the World's YWCA and the YMCA of the USA.
  When the Association was under attack, the office was the main recipient of letters of complaint and responsible for fashioning responses to explain the YWCA's position, and calm the membership, financial donors, and the general public. This was always a challenging task because there were few periods when the YWCA wasn't under attack for something, but it was particularly tricky from the red-baiting of the late 1940s through the Civil Rights movement in the 1950s and 1960s to women's liberation, anti-Vietnam war, and Equal Rights Amendment advocacy from the late 1960s into the early 1980s.
  In its role as steward of the National Association, General Administration was responsible for the effective administration of national staff, and oversaw various examinations of the Association's "purpose," and strategic planning efforts. It maintained a close association with financial development and public relations functions, both of which were, at times, part of General Administration and sometimes separate departments. The office also handled communications with Association attorneys over a wide variety of issues from trademark infringement to tax exemption status to membership policy to lawsuits against Community Associations in which the National Association was named as a co-defendant.
  General Administration committees and councils set work standards, wrote staff manuals, and developed policies and procedures that were specific to the workings of the national headquarters, but could also be models of effective office administration for Community YWCAs and organizations in general.
  In overseeing general personnel matters related to the national staff, the administrative office dealt with union issues, navigating the complexities of being an employer while also advocating publicly on behalf of the rights of workers. The goal of the National Association was always to be a model employer, so it was not easy when its own staff began to express a desire for union representation beginning in 1936. After five difficult years the National Board agreed to recognize the union of maintenance, clerical and professional staff.
  After World War II, the National Association's role in program activities became less about developing effective programs and program materials and more about soliciting funding and administering grants. Prior to this time, the administrative office had little involvement in the creation of programs and program materials. With the shift away from creating and toward administering program became more the province of the administrative office. Other types of programs, developed in the 1990s, such as the Race Against Racism and Week Without Violence, were national public awareness projects in which YWCA officers played important roles as speakers and participants in public event.
  Once program and publication activity was scaled back, the program and publication staffs were reduced and General Administration took over some of the basic communication with Community and Student Associations mainly by means of regular mailings beginning about 1971.
  The National Board's decision to sell the national headquarters building in 1982 was partly an economic decision-the sale of valuable Manhattan real estate provided much-needed funds-and partly a reflection of the reduced size of the national office.
  In the 1990s, the Communications and Knowledge Sharing Project emerged from a combination of factors including dissatisfaction among Community Associations with the performance of the national office, a need to address the challenges of record-keeping with an ever-shrinking staff, and a desire to take advantage of the possibilities offered by technology. Cambridge Management Consultants were engaged to identify the needs and work out a method for addressing them. The resulting 'Web-based communications platform' known as YWLink, was intended to allow communication between Member Associations, between the national office and the Associations, provide for the posting of materials that could be shared across the Association, and submission of some of the statistical and other reports required for maintaining affiliation in the National Association. Though the National Association had invested a considerable sum in developing the system, it ultimately proved too expensive and complicated for most Member Associations and was soon abandoned.
  With the 1999-2000 reorganization, the national administrative office was much reduced and moved from New York to Washington, DC where it shared facilities with the public policy advocacy office that had been established there circa 1991.
  Administrative History
  1907-08 Home Department
  1909-19 General Secretary/Headquarters Secretaries
  1920-59 General Administration
  1960-2000 Executive Office
  Scope and Content
  The records retention policy of the YWCA of the USA generally called for saving correspondence for only five years and then discarding it. This meant that for the period during which the Central File was most vigorously maintained (1907 through the early 1950s) little correspondence ended up integrated into the Central File and retained for historical reference. Since a substantial amount of the work of General Administration was correspondence, documentation of its overall work is spotty.
  Even so, the surviving materials do contain an unusual amount of correspondence and also some texts of speeches. There are also reports, memoranda, drafts, newspaper clippings, programs, committee materials, publications, and other administrative materials.
  General Administration files reveal the part played by Association officers in activities that are more fully documented in the records of other departments, such as Public Affairs.
  Committee, Commission, and Council records associated with national staff document such things as the establishment of work standards, how to evaluate staff work, office policies, and scheduling of travel and attendance at conferences.
  The section on Controversy and the YWCA chronicles the more controversial aspects of the YWCA program, and highlights the ways in which the YWCA had to defend itself against charges of communism.
  General Administration files also contain the primary documentation of the YWCA of the USA's relationships with other organizations especially its participation in the World YWCA, and its ever-complicated relations with the YMCA of the USA.
  Microfilmed Records, 1906-70 only
  [see Microfilmed Records Reel List]
  With the exception of the Minutes and Reports, there is not a great deal of overlap between the microfilmed materials and the surviving paper records. Both should be consulted.
  General Administration materials can be found on the microfilm in:
  Minutes and Reports
  Records of Committees concerned with day-to-day operations of the Association can be found under:
  Buildings Committee
  Business Committee
  Cafeteria Committee
  Evaluation Committee
  Headquarters Services Committee
  Hospitality Committee
  Methods Council
  Office Council
  Office Department Committee
  Office Management Council
  Office Services Committee
  Schedule Committee
  Secretaries' Meetings
  Records of Committees overseeing relationships with other organizations can be found under:
  Cooperation Committee
  Interchurch World Movement
  YMCA-YWCA Cooperation
  Subject Files
  Materials related to day-to-day operations of headquarters and to national staff can be found under:
  General Administration
  Headquarters Services
  Insurance
  National Board
  Office Services
  Personnel Policies and Services
  YWCA
  Materials related to legal issues can be found under:
  Copyrights
  Legal
  Reprint Privilege
  Symbols
  YWCA, Name and Symbols
  Materials about relationships with other Organizations can be found under:
  Government--United States
  Outside Organizations (includes World YWCA and YMCA among others)
  Original Format Records, 1907-2001, 21.5 linear ft.
  [see Original Format Records folder list]
  The bulk of the original format records were created after microfilming was finished, but there are also significant materials from the 1940s-70, particularly in Subseries B. Controversy and Subseries M. Racial Justice. Of special note is a small amount of the General Secretary's correspondence to National Board and staff members, 1907-12; mailings to Community and Student Associations in Subseries C. Correspondence; and materials about relations with the staff union in Subseries H. National Office/National Staff.
  The original format records are arranged in 15 Subseries as follows:
  Subseries A. Conferences/Meetings/Summits chronicles the YWCA officers' role as public face of the National Association at various conferences and meetings. Included here are records of their participation in national and international events that were not sponsored by the YWCA. None of these materials are included on the microfilm. They are arranged chronologically.
  Subseries B. Controversy is a correspondence, subject, and reference file compiled at the National Office to respond to negative publicity and a wide variety of attacks on the YWCA. The materials are arranged more-or-less chronologically and grouped by topic: labor in the 1930s and 1940s, communism in the 1940s and 1950s, racial justice in the 1960s and 1970s, anti-Vietnam war and women's movement in the 1970s, the Equal Rights Amendment in the early 1980s. Included is correspondence with the general public, with YWCA members and Member Associations; publications; newspaper clippings; and reports.
  Subseries C. Correspondence contains a small amount of general correspondence and correspondence with state and federal government agencies. The bulk is with YWCA groups and Associations about YWCA issues and arrangements for visits by national staff and officers. Included are mailings to Associations (1971-2001). Most of these materials are not on the microfilm.
  Subseries D. Events consists of materials related to the planning and program of miscellaneous YWCA events such as the "Celebration of '600'" at the time of the sale of the YWCA headquarters building in 1982, and memorial services for Board and staff held during National Board meetings, 1969-91. Most of these materials are not on the microfilm.
  Subseries E. Legal materials include correspondence with YWCA attorneys about a variety of legal issues including copyrights and trademarks, pending lawsuits, and the impact of various state and federal laws and Supreme Court rulings on the YWCA. There is also correspondence about registrations and renewals of trademarks and requests for permission to use YWCA copyrighted materials. Most is not included in the microfilm.
  Subseries F. Membership is primarily proposals and correspondence with firms late 1990s 'membership marketing campaign.'
  The bulk of Subseries G. Mission/Purpose is records of the Commission to Study the YWCA as a Christian Movement (1959-74), much of which is included on the microfilm. There are also other materials about the YWCA as a women's organization, and controversy over the inclusion of the phrase 'by any means necessary' in the YWCA's purpose statement.
  Subseries H. National Office/National Staff is made up of general and miscellaneous materials describing overall staff and office policies, procedures, and events. There are extensive minutes of Committees, Councils and Departments responsible for facilities management, clerical and business functions, personnel policies, and standards of work. Publications include staff manuals and a newsletter. As elsewhere in the records, the reports (1908-41) are a rich source, here detailing the inner workings of headquarters. Training materials (1976-2000) provide information about staff orientation sessions and workshops on a variety of other topics from improving organizational effectiveness to racism and heterosexism. The Union materials are an extensive chronological record (1939-99) containing correspondence, clippings, minutes, research materials, contract offers and agreements.
  Subseries I. Organizations documents the YWCA's relations with various religious, social welfare, and social work organizations plus funding foundations. Included are correspondence, clippings, publications, notes, and reference materials. World YWCA and YMCA of the USA files are especially extensive. Included are small files of correspondence with various national YWCAs around the world (1967-2002).
  The bulk of Subseries J. Programs and Projects is records of the Communications and Knowledge Sharing Project (1998-99), Education for Global Responsibility (1993-97) and the YWCA Intervention Programs (1971-77). There are also a few small files on other programs and projects. Most of these materials are not included in the microfilm.
  Subseries K. Public Relations documents the Executive Office's interactions with public relations consultants as part of the National Association's efforts to improve public awareness of the YWCA of the USA in the 1980s and 1990s.
  Files in Subseries L. Publications consist of Executive Office input and drafts for YWCA publications, plus copies of Emissaries, a newsletter for former National Board members.
  Subseries M. Racial Justice documents the Executive Office's participation in the work of the National Association and various of its committees on desegregation, other Civil Rights movement activities, and fair employment practices, primarily dated 1955 to 1967. Included is correspondence from Community Associations about Civil Rights Movement activities, 1963-65.
  Subseries N. Reports contains scattered reports by YWCA of the USA officers (1907-2000) and two reports about the operation of the national offices (1958 and 1959).
  Subseries O. Speeches and Statements contains texts of and notes for speeches and statements by YWCA National Presidents and Executive Directors. The bulk were delivered by Prema Mathai-Davis between 1994 and 1998.
  Related Materials
  Due to the central nature of the office, its work is reflected in materials found throughout the National Association records. Key materials can also be found by consulting:
  National Board minutes and reports in RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD
  The AssociationMonthly/Womans Press/YWCA Magazine in SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS of RECORD GROUP 6 is an excellent source for most topics.
  National Convention records, particularly reports to Convention by YWCA officers in RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES.
  Materials about the various reorganizations of national staff and office structure can be found in RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY
  Additional materials related to controversies can be found in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM, under Public Advocacy, Interracial, and Religion
  Additional materials about the YWCA's Mission/Purpose can be found in RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY and in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM under Religion.
  General reference files on the World YWCA and various national YWCAs are filed in RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY
  Community Associations files in RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS have information about national officers' and staffs' speaking engagements
  RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS included videotaped presentations about the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission lawsuit against the YWCA of Tucson and the YWCA of the U.S.A. Also included are audio and videotapes of selected National staff meetings, parties, and training events.
- SERIES II. BUILDINGS AND PROPERTIES
  Overview (see below for detailed information about specific properties)
  From the formation of the YWCA of the USA in 1906, the National Association has owned and leased a variety of properties for Association activities. At the beginning, these consisted of leased spaces in New York City for a headquarters and the National Training School, a continuation of the predecessor American Committee's Secretaries' Training Institute in Chicago.
  These functions were combined into one building with the construction of the national headquarters building at the corner of Lexington Avenue and 52nd Street in 1912. [see National Headquarters below] In 1913 the National Association was given property in Pacific Grove, California, for the development of a conference and meeting facility for the western region. [see Asilomar below]
  During World War I, the National Association acquired a number of properties all over the U.S. where it constructed housing for war workers, and 'Hostess Houses' for servicemen and their families. Most of these properties were sold soon after the war, but two remained in possession of the National Association. [see Grace Dodge Hotel and Chautauqua Hospitality House below]
  Economic hard times after the war and during the Great Depression made the National Association wary of the financial and administrative responsibilities associated with properties and buildings. When buyers could be found, properties were sold. Some, such as Asilomar, spent years in limbo until finally finding buyers. Over the years, other properties were offered as gifts to the National Association. Some were accepted on a trial basis and most often sold within a decade of the gift. [see Altamont and Fletcher Farm below]
  The National Association became involved in property management again in the 1980s after the Max C. Fleishmann Foundation of Reno, Nevada, announced that it wanted to distribute all of its assets and go out of business. The National Association took the opportunity to submit several proposals to the Foundation aimed at achieving some of its planning goals. In response to changing trends, especially among the volunteer work force, the Association had committed itself to a renewed emphasis on leadership training for the 1980s. In addition, a 1977 planning study by the Human Services Design Laboratory at Case Western Reserve University had recommended increasing the YWCA presence in the southwestern U.S. The proposal with the most appeal for the Fleishmann Foundation was a grant for the construction of a 'leadership development center' in the southwest. In addition, as regional offices and staffs had been reduced, the membership was feeling more and more that the national office was out of touch with their concerns and interests. The placement of a National Association center outside of New York was seen as a potential tool for addressing those concerns.
  A site was selected in Phoenix, Arizona, causing some controversy among Association membership due to the apparent inconsistency of building in a state that had not ratified the Equal Rights Amendment, a YWCA public policy priority since 1973. Citing the need for a "strong presence…in areas which most need the commitment of the YWCA to racial justice and equality for women," the YWCA went ahead with the construction. Dedicated in 1983, the Leadership Development Center was a year-round, non-residential training center for YWCA staff that could also be rented by similar groups.